Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. John R. Maher Papers, 1970-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. John R. Maher papers 1970-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
3 linear feet Extent: 2100 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. John R. Maher was an executive for JWT specializing in corporate development as well as account management. The John R. Maher Papers date from 1974 through 1986, with the bulk of the material spanning 1985-1986, roughly the period during which Maher managed corporate development for JWT. The collection contains information regarding companies proposed for acquisition by JWT; details from the acquisition of Winona Research; research and presentations regarding the state of advertising in China; strategic planning information for JWT Group and its subsidiaries; as well as some information about mega mergers and so called mega agencies. The materials include correspondence, reports, news clippings, presentation slides, corporate logos, contracts, financial documents, revenue projections, and promotional brochures. Companies mentioned in the files include Hill & Knowlton; Gallop Organization; Kobs and Brady; Simmons Market Research Bureau; and Towers, Perrin, Forster & Crosby. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00725
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. John R. Maher Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Biographical Note
March 9, 1932 Born, Brooklyn, NY
1953-1956 Served in U.S. Navy
1962 Account Supervisor, Benton & Bowles
1967 Director of Advertising and Promotion, Continental Airlines
1974 Account Director, J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT)
1976 General Manager, JWT Washington Office
1979 Deputy Manager, JWT North American Operations (New York Office)
1981 Senior Vice President, JWT Operations
1982 Group Account Director, JWT
1985 Placed in charge of Corporate Development, JWT Group
1986 Market Research Bureau (MRB Group) acquires Winona Research
1987 Elected Vice President of MRB Group
Collection Overview
The John R. Maher Papers date from 1974 through 1986, with the bulk of the material spanning 1985-1986, roughly the period during which Maher managed corporate development for JWT. The collection contains information regarding companies proposed for acquisition by JWT; details from the acquisition of Winona Research; research and presentations regarding the state of advertising in China; strategic planning information for JWT Group and its subsidiaries; as well as some information about mega mergers and so called mega agencies. The materials include correspondence, reports, news clippings, presentation slides, corporate logos, contracts, financial documents, revenue projections, and promotional brochures. Companies mentioned in the files include Hill & Knowlton; Gallop Organization; Kobs and Brady; Simmons Market Research Bureau; and Towers, Perrin, Forster & Crosby.
Collection Arrangement
This collection of general office files is arranged alphabetically. There are four major topic areas within the collection: China, potential acquisitions, strategic planning and Winona Research. There are also several folders regarding the phenomenon of mega agencies and mega mergers wherein agencies continually acquire other agencies, research into expanding the JWT Company into the Southwestern United States, Kellogg company client report, start up documents for the MRB group, and presentations on USA brand leadership and the future of networks. Materials in all folders include general papers including notes, correspondence, presentations, revenue projections and clippings from newspapers and magazines. Other materials include black and white slides and artwork for logos.
Subject Headings
Maher, John R., 1932-; J. Walter Thompson Company; Hill and Knowlton, Inc.; Simmons Market Research Bureau; Towers, Perrin, Forster & Crosby; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising -- China; Advertising -- China -- History; Advertising agencies -- Management; Consolidation and merger of corporations; Strategic Planning; Slides; Logos; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials can be found in the following Hartman Cetner Collections of the J. Walter thompson Company Archives:
Biographical Information, 1916-1998, bulk 1960s-1980s
Frankfurt Office. Advertisements Collection, 1950-1991 and undated
Iconographic Collection, 1848-2005 and undated
Writings and Speeches, 1912-2000 and undated
Additional related material may be located in:
Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records, 1943-2003 and undated
Contents of Collection
- General Office Files, 1974-1986, (5 boxes)
  Contains information regarding companies proposed for acquisition by JWT; details from the acquisition of Winona Research; research and presentations regarding the state of advertising in China; strategic planning information for JWT Group and its subsidiaries; as well as some information about mega mergers and so called mega agencies. Materials include correspondence, notes, reports, news clippings, presentation slides, logos, contracts, financial documents, revenue projections, and promotional brochures.
  - China, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    Contains research materials on advertising in China, including news clippings; reports; materials related to preparing a trip to China; slides from a presentation given on advertising in China; and information about JWT client activity in China.
    - China research communications and planning, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - China research materials, 1979-1985, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - JWT Client Involvement in China and Communications Report, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Presentation printouts and slides, 1985 Sept. 12 (Box 1)
    - Advertising Review and Opportunities for JWT, report, 1985 June 21, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Roy Glah clippings and correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - Hill and Knowlton lobbying, circa 1985 (Box 1)
  - JWT Compant Germany, organizational research and evaluations, 1975-1986, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Kellogg: Compensation study and reports, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Mega agency presentation and clippings, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Mega agency presentation text and printed slides, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Mega mergers, clippings and handwritten notes, 1974-1986 and undated (Box 2)
  - MRB Group startup materials, correspondence, logo artwork, policies, planning and clippings, 1984-1986 and undated (Box 2)
  - Network Television Today and Tomorrow speech, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Potential acquisitions, 1981-1986
    Contains information regarding companies JWT either considered or attempted to acquire. Acquisition papers include correspondence; company financial statements; revenue projections; authorization to negotiate acquisition forms; company research; clippings; acquisition strategy information; and promotional materials.
    - Gallop Organization acquisition papers, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
    - Hank Meyers associates, Inc. acquisition papers, 1981-1986 (Box 2)
    - Kobs and Brady acquistion papers, 1984-1986, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Krupp Taylor acquisition papers, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Overview of acquisition candidates, acquistion papers, 1985-1986, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Research for acquisition candidates, 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - Response Communications, Inc. acquisition papers, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
    - Ted Thomas Associates, Inc. acquisition papers, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    - Towers, Perrin, Forster & Crosby acquistion papers, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - William Douglas McAdams, Inc. acquistion papers, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Strategic planning, 1985-1986
    Contains strategic planning and review documents and presentations regarding JWT Group and its subsidiaries.
    - Hill and Knowlton Strategic Plan for years 1986-1988, undated (Box 3)
    - Investment research reports, background data, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - JWT Company Marketing Plan for 1985-1987 and Strategic Review for Operations Committee meeting, 1985 (Box 4)
    - JWT Company Strategic Plan and Review for 1985-1987, 1985 Sept. 17 (Box 4)
    - JWT Company Strategic Plan presentation to Executive Committee, 1986 Aug.-Sept. (Box 4)
    - JWT Group Strategic Plan for Board of Directors meeting, 1985 Dec. 3 (Box 4)
    - JWT Group Strategic Review and Plan for Board of Directors meeting, 1985 Dec. 3 (Box 4)
    - JWT Group Strategic Review, circa 1986 (Box 4)
    - Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein, Inc. Strategic Plan Review presentation, 1985 June 26 (Box 4)
    - Simmons Market Research Bureau, Strategic Plan Review presentation, 1985 May 28 (Box 4)
  - Texas expansion research and reports, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - USA Brand Leadership Report, clippings, and notes, 1981-1984 (Box 4)
  - Winona Research, 1982-1986 (Box 5)
    Contains acquisiton papers and contracts from the acquisition of Winona Research by JWT, including correspondence; company financial statements; revenue projections; authorization to negotiate acquisition forms; company research; clippings; acquisition strategy information; and promotional materials.
    - Acquistion papers and contracts, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Company financial documents, 1982-1985 (Box 5)
    - Due dilligence review by Price Waterhouse, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Purchase agreement drafts, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 5)